<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>codecorner</title>
    <link href="https://65982b00482624254b19b6dc--nimble-torte-bd2b7a.netlify.app/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://65982b00482624254b19b6dc--nimble-torte-bd2b7a.netlify.app" />
    <updated>2024-01-05T17:49:35+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Tebogo Mahlomoja</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://65982b00482624254b19b6dc--nimble-torte-bd2b7a.netlify.app</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Understanding Kubernetes - Part 2.</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tebogo Mahlomoja</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://65982b00482624254b19b6dc--nimble-torte-bd2b7a.netlify.app/understanding-kubernetes-2.html"/>
        <id>https://65982b00482624254b19b6dc--nimble-torte-bd2b7a.netlify.app/understanding-kubernetes-2.html</id>

        <updated>2024-01-05T17:49:35+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Control Plane Components and Distributed Nature Kubernetes, being a distributed system, consists of several components that collaborate to maintain the desired state of the cluster. At its core are the control plane components, which manage and control the cluster's operation. The distributed nature of Kubernetes&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Control Plane Components and Distributed Nature</h2>
<p dir="auto">Kubernetes, being a distributed system, consists of several components that collaborate to maintain the desired state of the cluster. At its core are the control plane components, which manage and control the cluster's operation. The distributed nature of Kubernetes allows these components to work together across multiple nodes, ensuring high availability and fault tolerance.</p>
<h2 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Control Plane Components</h2>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">etcd</h3>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Description:</strong> etcd is a distributed key-value store that stores the cluster's configuration data, including cluster state, configurations, and metadata. It serves as Kubernetes' primary database and ensures high availability and consistency.</p>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">API Server</h3>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Description:</strong> The API Server acts as the front-end for the Kubernetes control plane. It exposes the Kubernetes API, which allows users, other components, and external services to interact with the cluster. All administrative tasks and communication with other components occur through the API Server.</p>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Scheduler</h3>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Description:</strong> The Scheduler is responsible for assigning pods to nodes based on resource availability, constraints, policies, and workload requirements. It decides which node should run a particular pod, optimizing resource utilization and maintaining workload balance.</p>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Controller Manager</h3>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Description:</strong> The Controller Manager consists of multiple controllers that handle different aspects of the cluster's state. Each controller watches the cluster's state through the API Server and takes corrective actions to ensure that the actual state matches the desired state defined in the cluster's configuration.</p>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Distributed Nature of Kubernetes</h3>
<p dir="auto">Kubernetes operates in a distributed manner, meaning its components are spread across multiple nodes within the cluster. This distribution ensures fault tolerance and high availability by preventing a single point of failure. Each control plane component runs on multiple nodes, and when one node fails, another node automatically takes over its responsibilities.</p>
<h2 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Control Loops and Reconciliation</h2>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Control Loops</h3>
<p dir="auto">Kubernetes employs control loops to maintain the desired state of the cluster continuously. These control loops are continuously running processes within each controller that perform reconciliation—comparing the actual state of the cluster with the desired state and taking necessary actions to converge them.</p>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Reconciliation Process</h3>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Observation:</strong> Controllers watch the cluster's current state by querying the API Server for the desired configuration.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Comparison:</strong> The observed state is compared against the desired state specified in the configuration.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Decision Making:</strong> If there are any discrepancies between the observed and desired states, the controller makes decisions to reconcile the differences.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Action:</strong> The controller takes appropriate actions to bring the actual state in line with the desired state, either by creating, deleting, or updating resources.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Example of Reconciliation</h3>
<p dir="auto">Consider the ReplicaSet controller, responsible for maintaining a specified number of identical pods. If it observes fewer pods than the desired count:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Observation: The controller checks the actual number of pods.</li>
<li>Comparison: Compares this count with the desired count specified in the ReplicaSet.</li>
<li>Decision Making: Recognizes the shortfall and decides to create more pods.</li>
<li>Action: Initiates the creation of additional pods to meet the desired count.</li>
</ul>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Conclusion</h3>
<p dir="auto">The control plane components of Kubernetes work collaboratively in a distributed environment, ensuring the cluster's stability, fault tolerance, and adherence to the desired state. Through control loops and reconciliation processes, Kubernetes maintains the system's health by continuously monitoring and adjusting its components, thereby enabling a resilient and self-healing infrastructure for containerized applications. Understanding these control plane components and their distributed nature is crucial for managing and operating Kubernetes clusters effectively.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Understanding Kubernetes - Part 1.</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tebogo Mahlomoja</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://65982b00482624254b19b6dc--nimble-torte-bd2b7a.netlify.app/understanding-kubernetes.html"/>
        <id>https://65982b00482624254b19b6dc--nimble-torte-bd2b7a.netlify.app/understanding-kubernetes.html</id>

        <updated>2024-01-05T17:49:21+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    In the world of modern software development and deployment, Kubernetes has emerged as a leading orchestration tool for managing containerized applications. It simplifies the process of deploying, scaling, and managing containerized applications, providing a robust framework for automating various aspects of application management. Kubernetes, often&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p dir="auto">In the world of modern software development and deployment, Kubernetes has emerged as a leading orchestration tool for managing containerized applications. It simplifies the process of deploying, scaling, and managing containerized applications, providing a robust framework for automating various aspects of application management.</p>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">What is Kubernetes?</h3>
<p dir="auto">Kubernetes, often abbreviated as K8s, is an open-source container orchestration platform originally developed by Google. It automates the deployment, scaling, and management of containerized applications. Its primary objective is to abstract the underlying infrastructure and provide a consistent environment for deploying and managing applications across various environments, from local development setups to large-scale production clusters.</p>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Key Concepts in Kubernetes:</h3>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Pods:</strong> The basic unit of deployment in Kubernetes, representing one or more containers that share networking and storage resources.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Deployments:</strong> Manage the deployment of replicated applications, ensuring the desired state of a specific number of pods is maintained.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Services:</strong> Enable communication between different sets of pods, abstracting away individual IP addresses and providing a stable endpoint for accessing applications.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Persistent Volumes:</strong> Provide storage resources that exist beyond the lifecycle of a pod, allowing data to persist even if the pod is deleted.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Creating a Development Cluster using kind</h2>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">What is kind?</h3>
<p dir="auto">Kubernetes IN Docker (kind) is a tool that allows users to create Kubernetes clusters using Docker containers as nodes. It is particularly useful for testing and development purposes, providing a lightweight and easy-to-set-up environment to simulate a Kubernetes cluster.</p>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Creating a Kubernetes Cluster Imperatively using kind</h3>
<ol dir="auto">
<li><strong>Installation:</strong> Ensure Docker is installed on your machine.</li>
<li><strong>Install kind:</strong> Download and install kind according to the instructions for your operating system.</li>
<li><strong>Create a Cluster:</strong> Use the <code>kind create cluster</code> command to create a Kubernetes cluster. This command generates a configuration file and starts the cluster.</li>
</ol>
<div class="highlight highlight-source-shell notranslate position-relative overflow-auto" dir="auto">
<pre>kind create cluster --name my-cluster</pre>
</div>
<ol dir="auto" start="4">
<li><strong>Verify the Cluster:</strong> Use <code>kubectl</code> (Kubernetes command-line tool) to verify the cluster's status.</li>
</ol>
<div class="highlight highlight-source-shell notranslate position-relative overflow-auto" dir="auto">
<pre>kubectl cluster-info --context kind-my-cluster</pre>
</div>
<h3 dir="auto" tabindex="-1">Creating a Kubernetes Cluster Declaratively using kind</h3>
<p dir="auto">Instead of creating a cluster imperatively through commands, Kubernetes configurations can be used to define the cluster in a YAML file.</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li><strong>Create a Cluster Configuration File:</strong> Define the cluster's configuration in a YAML file (e.g., <code>cluster-config.yaml</code>).</li>
</ol>
<div class="highlight highlight-source-yaml notranslate position-relative overflow-auto" dir="auto">
<pre><span class="pl-ent">kind</span>: <span class="pl-s">Cluster</span>
<span class="pl-ent">apiVersion</span>: <span class="pl-s">kind.x-k8s.io/v1alpha4</span>
<span class="pl-ent">nodes</span>:
- <span class="pl-ent">role</span>: <span class="pl-s">control-plane</span>
- <span class="pl-ent">role</span>: <span class="pl-s">worker</span>
- <span class="pl-ent">role</span>: <span class="pl-s">worker</span></pre>
</div>
<ol dir="auto" start="2">
<li><strong>Create the Cluster using Configuration File:</strong> Use the <code>kind create cluster</code> command with the <code>--config</code> flag to create the cluster based on the configuration file.</li>
</ol>
<div class="highlight highlight-source-shell notranslate position-relative overflow-auto" dir="auto">
<pre>kind create cluster --name my-cluster --config cluster-config.yaml</pre>
</div>
<ol dir="auto" start="3">
<li><strong>Verify the Cluster:</strong> Use <code>kubectl</code> to ensure the cluster is created successfully.</li>
</ol>
<div class="highlight highlight-source-shell notranslate position-relative overflow-auto" dir="auto">
<pre>kubectl cluster-info --context kind-my-cluster</pre>
<h3 class="zeroclipboard-container"><span style="color: var(--headings-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: 1.60181em; font-weight: var(--font-weight-bold); letter-spacing: var(--letter-spacing);">Conclusion</span></h3>
</div>
<p dir="auto">Kubernetes simplifies the orchestration and management of containerized applications, providing a scalable and efficient platform for developers. Tools like kind enable the creation of Kubernetes clusters for development purposes, allowing developers to simulate and test applications locally before deploying them in production environments. Whether creating clusters imperatively or declaratively, understanding Kubernetes fundamentals empowers developers to harness its capabilities effectively, streamlining the development and deployment of modern applications.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
